Guide to the Edward G. Lawson papers, 1915-1937
Lawson, Edward G. papers, 1915-1937
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Edward G. Lawson papers, 1915-1937.
4237
Edward G. Lawson, 1884-1968.
3.4 cubic ft.
Photographs, a scrapbook, drawings, correspondence, and other materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Scrapbook kept by Lawson during his years as a student at the American Academy in Rome, as a "Prix de Rome" winner in landscape architecture. Includes photographs and measured drawings of buildings and architectural details, planting lists, plans, and elevations, primarily in Italy. Also, photographs of plans of American cemeteries in France and England, 1921; photographs of Lawson, and of a portrait of Lawson; photographs of unidentified architectural details and plans; measured drawings of unidentified details; and a postcard and note sent to Lawson. Bound volumes from the American Academy in Rome and Lantern slides of illustrations from Lawson's Rome Prize thesis
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Edward Godfrey Lawson was born in Buffalo, N.Y. on October 29, 1884. He attended Cornell University, receiving a B.S. in 1913 and a Master of Landscape Design in 1914. Awarded the "Prix de Rome" in Landscape Architecture in 1915, he studied at the American Academy in Rome, and was elected a fellow of the American Academy in 1920. During World War I, he served in the Italian Red Cross, from 1917 to 1919. From 1920 to 1922, Lawson planned military cemeteries in France, England, and Belgium for the U.S. Graves Registration Service, Paris. He returned to the United States, and was appointed assistant professor of landscape architecture at Cornell in 1922, where he taught until ca.1940. He worked for the House of Herbs, the first center of herb culture in the United States, until his retirement in 1964. On January 4, 1968, Lawson died at Winter Park, Florida.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Scrapbook kept by Lawson during his years as a student at the American Academy in Rome, as a "Prix de Rome" winner in landscape architecture. Includes photographs and measured drawings of buildings and architectural details, planting lists, plans, and elevations, primarily in Italy. Also, photographs of plans of American cemeteries in France and England, 1921; photographs of Lawson, and of a portrait of Lawson; photographs of unidentified architectural details and plans; measured drawings of unidentified details; and a postcard and note sent to Lawson.
Also bound volumes from the American Academy in Rome, with article and photographs of the Villa Gamberaia, by Edward Lawson, compiled by Edward Lawson, 1927; Villa Medici, Rome, written and compiled by Edward Lawson, 1930; Villa d'Este at Tivoli, by Michael Rapuano, compiled by Lawson, 1933; Villa Palmieri, Florence, by Michael Rapuano, compiled by Lawson, 1935; Villa Medici at Fiesole near Florence, by Norman T. Newton, compiled by Lawson, 1935; and Villa Cicogna Bisuschio, by Ralph E. Griswold, compiled by Lawson, 1937. Includes colored architectural drawing of the Villa Camberaia at Settignano created by Lawson.
Lantern slides (8) of illustrations from Lawson's Rome Prize thesis.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Lawson, Edward G. (Edward Godfrey), 1884-1968.; American Academy (Rome, Italy)
Subjects:
Landscape architecture.; Cemeteries--Landscape architecture.; National cemeteries, American.; Landscape architects.
Form and Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Sketches of architectural details, ca. 1915-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Sketches of architectural details, ca. 1915-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs (misc. plans and details), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lawson - portraits and photographs - projects, Williamsport, Pa. and Falls Village, Ct., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- European cemeteries (plans), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, lists, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Printed maps and articles, n.d., 1915-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Scrapbook, ca. 1915-1920 (Box 1)
- Garden Details, Foun (Box 2)
- Garden Details, Foun (Box 3)
- Fountains, Garden De (Box 4)
- Sculpture (Box 5)
- Renaissance Interior (Box 6)
- Renaissance I[taly] (Box 7)
- Inoui, NY (?) Gardens and Terraces drawing, removed from collection #1380, 1915 (Box 8)
- 8 lantern slides of illustrations from Lawson's Rome Prize thesis, n.d. (Box 9)
- Architectural details on yellow tracing paper (5 pieces), Map case
- Architectural drawing of the Villa Gamberaia, Map case